A Guide to the Governor's Office, Executive Mansion Director, Records, 1973-1995
Library of Virginia
- Citizens' Advisory Council on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion 1973-1989 (Box 5-7)
  - Correspondence 1973-1989 (Box 6)
    - 1982 Correspondence 1982 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - 1983 Correspondence 1983 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - 1984 Correspondence 1984 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - 1985 Correspondence 1985 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - 1987 Correspondence 1987 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - 1988 Correspondence 1988 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - 1989 Correspondence 1989 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Financial Files 1973-1979 (Box 6-7)
    Arranged chronologically. Contains information regarding donations and purchases made by the Citizens' Advisory Council on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion from 1973 until 1989. This series also includes invoices for repair and restoration work on items within the Mansion. Members of the Citizens' Advisory Council on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion transferred these files to the Office of the Director of the Executive Mansion in 1987. These materials compliment the materials found in the Library of Virginia accession 35652 from the Citizens' Advisory Council on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion.
    - 1973 Financial 1973 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - 1974 Financial 1974 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - 1975 Financial 1975 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - 1976 Financial 1976 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - 1977 Financial 1977 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - 1978 Financial 1978 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - 1979 Financial 1979 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - 1979 Financial 1979 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - 1980 Financial 1980 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1981 Financial 1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1982 Financial 1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1983 Financial 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1984 Financial 1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1985 Financial 1985 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1987 Financial 1987 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1988 Financial 1988 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1989 Financial 1989 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- 175th Anniversary of the Executive Mansion 1987-1989 (Box 7)
  Arranged into two (2) subseries: Correspondence and Other Materials, 1987-1989; and Financial Files, 1987-1989. Contains correspondence and financial information relating to the events surrounding the 175th Anniversary of the Executive Mansion. The Citizens' Advisory Council on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion (formerly the Citizens' Advisory Committee on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion) was responsible for the developing of activities and events for the celebration. Members of the Citizens' Advisory Council on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion transferred these files to the Office of the Director of the Executive Mansion in 1987.
  - Correspondence and Other Materials (Box 7)
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Contains correspondence and other materials relating to the 1988 celebration of the 175th anniversary of the Executive Mansion.
    - Correspondence - Contributions (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - Contributor's Thank You Letters (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence - General (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence - General Thank You Letters (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence - Survey Letters/ First Ladies' Letter (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Education Committee 1987 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Event 1988 June 25 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Garden Week 1988 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - General Information (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Library Book References (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Lists (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Meeting Minutes 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Office Insurance (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Responses to Invitations to be on Commission (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Statewide Essay Contest (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Steering Committee (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Financial Files (Box 7)
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Contains budget information, invoices, financial statements and statements of contributions to the 175th Anniversary of the Executive Mansion Committee.
    - Bills Paid: A (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Bills Paid: B (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Bills Paid: C (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Bills Paid: D (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Bills Paid: E (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Bills Paid: F (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Bills Paid: G (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Bills Paid: H (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Bills Paid: I-J (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Bills Paid: K-L (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Bills Paid: M (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Bills Paid: N (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Bills Paid: P (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Bills Paid: R (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Bills Paid: S (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Bills Paid: T (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Bills Paid: U-V (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Bills Paid: W (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Bills Paid: X, Y, Z (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Budget, Schedule of Events Proposals 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Contributions 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Financial Statements (Box 7, Folder 47)
- Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Contains correspondence, memos and other items not directly related to the Executive Mansion and its functions.
  - 200th Anniversary of the Bill of Rights Informational Materials (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence regarding gifts received, Baliles administration 1986-1989 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Internship, Fall 1992 - Elizabeth Chisman Museum education Project 1992 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Mattaponi Indians News Article 1995 June (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Notes regarding photographs (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Sheet Music (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Virginia Executive Institute Alumni Association, Fall 1992 1992 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Virginia State Library & Archives (Box 7, Folder 55)
- Architectural Drawings, Renderings and other plans (Box 7, 11)
  Arranged chronologically. Most items are found in Box 11, Oversize. Some items were removed from folders in other series -- notations of such actions accompany the item and are indicated in the folder listing for each series.
  - "Basement Plan. Executive Mansion. Richmond, Virginia." No name or date. SOE File No. 138 2.17. On yellow paper. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Detail of cabinets (in dining room) with fa硤e detail. Photocopy. No name or date. [Name on detail is that of Mansion Director.] Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Renovation Project Notes. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Detail of cabinets with fa硤e and moulding details. Photocopy. No name or date. [Name on detail is that of Mansion Director.] Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Renovation Project Notes. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Drawing of detail of niche in Dining Room. Mounted on foamcore, colored pencil shading. No name or date. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Renovation Project Notes. (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Drawing of first floor of Mansion -- North and South Ballrooms and Dining Room -- with indication of table placement for events. No name or date. Removed from Executive Mansion, DGS/Special Projects Long Range Improvement Planning Study for Use of the Executive Mansion (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Drawing of Formal Garden with indication of plantings. Title:"Formal Garden, Overlay #2000-9." Photocopy. No name or date. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Grounds - Executive Mansion (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "First Floor Plan. Executive Mansion. Richmond, Virginia." No name or date. SOE File NO. 138 2.17. Has notations in green regarding interior details. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Floor plan of first floor of Executive Mansion, with table placements in north and south ballrooms and dining room. Photocopy. No name or date. 2 table arrangements, 2 copies of each. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Renovation Project Notes. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Second Floor Plan. Executive Mansion. Richmond, Virginia." No name or date. SOE file number 138 2.17. On yellow paper. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Photocopy of "A Plan for the City of Richmond" by Richard Young. From Weddell, Alexander W. Richmond Virginia in Old Prints, 1737-1887 (Richmond: Johnson Publishing Company, 1932). 2 copies (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Photocopy of map/plan of Capitol Square area of Richmond. From the Virginia State Library. Source unknown. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Plans of first and second floors of Executive Mansion. No name or date. Contains 3 copies of the second floor plan. (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - "Suggested Revisions for the Gardens and Grounds." Stanley W. Abbott, 11-30-70. #2000-6 rev. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Grounds - Executive Mansion 1970 Nov 30 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - "Virginia Governor's Mansion - Dining Room. H.S.T.R. May 1974." Detail of niche "as is" and "reworked." Also includes tracing attached to back. 1974 May (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - "Executive Mansion Ballroom" with notations regarding furniture owned by and to be acquired by the Mansion. RAC Interior Design. 1976 Nov (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Executive Mansion Ballroom" without furniture notations. RAC Interior Design. 1976 Nov (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "Executive Mansion Proposed Design Sketches." Sketches of windows and window treatments for breakfast room and dining room. RAC Interior Design. William E. Joel, II 1978 July (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "The Carved Stone Fountain" Overall Ht. 7'-11" Diameter of top bowl 3'-5" Lower Bowl 4'-6"diameter." Removed from Executive Mansion, Citizens' Advisory Committee on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion, 1980 Correspondence. Letter dated 7/7/80 from Tom Crowther (filed chronologically with response letter dated 10/9/80). 1980 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "The Terra Cotta Dolphin Fountain on Stone Bases" Surmounted by a lead figure - overall Ht. 5'-9" Diameter of Bowl 4'-0". Removed from Executive Mansion, Citizens' Advisory Committee on Furnishing and Interpreting the Executive Mansion, 1980 Correspondence. Letter dated 7/7/80 from Tom Crowther (filed chronologically with response letter dated 10/9/80). 1980 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - "Scheme #1 Proposed Second Floor Plan. Alterations to Living Quarters. Plan shows dust partitions as proposed and work access." Howard Shockey and Sons, Inc. 3-12-82, 3-29-82. 1982 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - "Alterations to Living Quarters The Virginia Executive Mansion Richmond Virginia." "Shows schematic layout with dotted lines showing construction to be removed and shaded lines showing new construction." Howard Shockey and Sons, Inc. 3-12-82, 3-29-82. 1982 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - "Alterations to Basement Area The Virginia Executive Mansion Richmond Virginia." Howard Shockey and Sons, Inc. 3-12-82, 3-29-82. 1982 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - "Alterations to The Guest House The Virginia Executive Mansion Richmond Virginia." First Floor. Howard Shockey and Sons, Inc. 3-12-82, 3-29-82. 1982 (Box 11, Folder 19+)
  - "Alterations to The Guest House The Virginia Executive Mansion Richmond Virginia." Second Floor. Howard Shockey and Sons, Inc. 3-12-82, 3-29-82. 1982 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - "Alterations to Living Quarters The Virginia Executive Mansion Richmond Virginia." "Shows schematic layout upon completion of the second floor." Howard Shockey and Sons, Inc. 3-12-82, 3-29-82. 1982 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - "Flower Arranging Room." Howard Shockey and Sons, Inc. 10-7-82. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Grounds - Executive Mansion 1982 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Floor plans (Basement, First and Second Floors), with electrical notes. 1986. No name. 3 pages. 1986 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Drawing of basement plan of Mansion. No name or date [circa 1987]. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Historical American Building Survey Team 1987 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Illustration of exterior elevation. "View of Terrace from South Garden." No name or date [circa 1987]. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Historical American Building Survey Team 1987 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - First floor plan of the Executive Mansion with furniture designations and other items. No name or date [circa 1987]. 3 copies. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Historical American Building Survey Team 1987 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - "Renovations to the Executive Mansion Capitol Square" Hanbury Evans Newill Vlattas. 10-30-90. Job No. 90027.00. Details of doors. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Renovation Project Notes. 1990 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Series of partial plans for providing handicapped access to the Mansion. Includes enlarged elevation, section thru ramp, profile of screen wall, plan of toilet for disabled, partial plan showing lift, partial plan showing ramp, and sectional elevation. Plans by Hanbury Evans Newill and Vlattas. No date. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Handicapped Access Project, 1991-1992. 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Details of handicapped restroom in cottage. Comprised of detail of door jamb, elevation of door, plan for toilet for disabled. Photocopy. Plan by Hanbury Evans Newill and Vlattas. No date. 2 copies. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Handicapped Access Project, 1991-1992. 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - "Modifications to the Executive Mansion for the Disabled." Hanbury Evans Newill and Vlattas. Project No. 9002703. By J.P.C. Hanbury. Dates: 12-31-91: 5-20-92: 6-8-92. 2 copies. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Handicapped Access Project, 1991-1992. 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - "Renovations to Existing Dining Room china Cabinets" Hanbury Evans Newill Vlattas and Co., 1990. Job no. 90027.00 Date: 1-15-93 on plan. Note on plan "New 2-8-93" Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Renovation Project Notes. 1993 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - "Painted plinth for niches (2 required) full size profiles." Hanbury Evans Newill Vlattas. 8-5-93. 2 copies. Removed from Executive Mansion DGS/Special Projects Renovation Project Notes. 1993 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Fax from Gallahan's Furniture with possible furniture for Mrs. Allen's office. Fax dated Feb. 6, 1994. Folder titled: Executive Mansion First Ladies Office and 2nd fl. Mansion plans 1994 (Box 7, Folder 59)
- Photographs, slides and negatives (Box 8-9)
  Arranged into seven (7) subseries. Contains photographs, slides and negatives depicting the Mansion, its occupants and events at the Mansion. Many of the photographs were previously used in brochures and other publications about the Executive Mansion, including William Seale's Virginia's Executive Mansion (1988). Photographs are from various sources including the Richmond Newspapers, the Valentine Museum, the Library of Virginia, and from private collections.
  - Photographs of Governors and their families (Box 8)
    Arranged alphabetically by last name. Contains photographs of former Governors of the Commonwealth of Virginia and their families.
    - Allen, George Felix (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Almond, James Lindsay, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Baliles, Gerald Lee (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Battle, John Stewart (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Byrd, Harry Flood (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Dalton, John Nichols (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Darden, Colgate Whitehead, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Godwin, Miles Edwin, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Harrison, Albertis Sydney, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Holton, Abner Linwood, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Montague, Andrew Jackson (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Peery, George Campbell (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Pollard, John Garland (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Price, James Hubert (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Robb, Charles Spittal (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Stanley, Thomas Bahnson (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Trinkle, Elbert Lee (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Tuck, William Munford (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Wilder, Lawrence Douglas (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Executive Mansion Exteriors (Box 8)
    Arranged alphabetically by subject. Contains photographs of the exteriors of the Executive Mansion. The date range is not clear, but there are photographs from before and after several of the exterior restorations of the Mansion.
    - Fountain (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Mansion Exterior, 175th Anniversary 1988 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Mansion Exterior with holiday decorations, probably 1992 1992 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Mansion Exterior, photographed by Katherine Wetzel 1996 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Mansion Exterior, dates unknown (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of Executive Mansion Interiors (Box 8)
    Arranged alphabetically by room. Contains photographs of unknown dates of the rooms in the Mansion. There are photographs from before and after the restoration of the Mansion to a Federal Period theme.
    - Dining Room (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Drawing Room (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Entrance Hall (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Family Quarters, not identified (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Lafayette Bedroom (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Mantel Details, Katherine Wetzel 1996 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Old Governor's Office (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - North Ballroom (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - South Ballroom (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Unknown (Governor's Bedroom) (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of events held at the Executive Mansion (Box 9)
    Arranged chronologically. Contains photographs of events that took place at the Executive Mansion. For more information about the specific events, including programs, see Series I: Event Files.
    - Virginia First Ladies Reunion 1982 Mar 24 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Executive Mansion Open House with Music by the Suzuki strings and Members from the Swift Creek Middle School Orchestra 1990 Dec 15 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Holiday Events 1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Holiday Tree Lighting 1992 Dec 9 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Holiday Tree Lighting 1992 Dec 9 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Mansion Interior and Exteriors, Garden Week 1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of events not held at the Executive Mansion (Box 9)
    One folder. Contains photographs from the First Ladies Conference in 1984. Mrs. Robb attended this conference which featured wives and daughters of former presidents of the United States.
    - First Ladies Conference, Grand Rapids Michigan 1984 Apr (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Contains one unknown photograph and one photographic reproduction of an 1860s lithograph.
    - Photograph of 1860s color lithograph (source: Virginia State Library and Archives) (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified photograph (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Negatives, Slides and Transparencies (Box 9)
    Arranged alphabetically by medium (negative, slide or transparency) and then chronologically. Contains negatives, slides and transparencies of photographs taken of the Mansion or at Mansion events. Prints of some of these materials may be found in Series VIII.
    - Negatives, Christmas 1991 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Negatives -- Interior and Exterior of Mansion, by Katherine Wetzel, 1996. Black and white, 4"x6" 16 items. 1996 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Negatives (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Slides from Historical American Building Survey 1987 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Slides of Mansion (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Transparencies -- Interior and Exterior of Mansion, by Katherine Wetzel, 1996. Color, 4"x6" 19 items. 1996 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Ephemera (Box 10)
  Arranged alphabetically by item title. Contains artifacts, videotapes, decorator samples, and one book.
  - Piece of marble in green velvet bag from unknown occasion. 2 items. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Samples of upholstery, carpet and wallpaper. Removed from DGS/Special Projects: Furnishing and Redecorating Private Quarters 1990-1991 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Sample of wallpaper. Removed from DGS/Special Projects: Painting/Wallpaper of first floor 1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Sample of wood blind. Removed from DGS/Special Projects: Wood Blinds and Ultraviolet Filtering Shades. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Videotape: Executive Mansion Hostess Seminar. Master Tape #2. Friday, September 11, 1992, 10-3pm. VHS Format. 1992 Sept 11 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - . Videotape: Executive Mansion Hostess Seminar. Tape #2. Thursday, October 7, 1993. VHS Format. 1993 Oct 7 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Our Governor's Mansions by Cathy Keating (New York: Abrams, 1997), 2 copies. 1997 (Box 10, Folder 7)